He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall.
And he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him, and they will praise and bless
and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels,
demons and saints.
In our time, many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism, to
see and to know reality as it truly is.
What is this spiritual reality like?
How do we engage with it well?
How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen De Young
host this live Colin Cho focused on enchantment in creation.
union of the scene and unseen as
made by God and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Hey everybody, welcome back.
Good evening, all of you giant killers and dragon slayers,
but not werewolf hunters.
You are listening to the Lord of Spirits podcast.
My co-host, Father Stephen D'Yung,
is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana.
And I'm Father-Intersteven Damick
in the Burrow of Emmaus, Pennsylvania.
If you're listening to us live,
You can call at h55afrad
EI-O, 855-237-2346.
Mantras Kachoo-Di is taking those calls tonight
and we're gonna get to those in the second part of the show.
Tonight we're gonna be talking about the soul.
What is it really?
Yeah, what's up with that?
Yeah, what is up with that?
This is one of those words that gets used a lot
by Christians all the time.
But often without a clear sense of what it is
even how the way that we use the word has been.
deeply influenced by non-Christian philosophies. So how is the soul actually understood in the
scriptures? And how different is that from the common conception? So that's what we're going to
be talking about tonight. I'm not sure if you're going to walk away feeling like your mind is more
bent or a little bit clearer, but I guess we'll just see what happens. So number one, bro, you didn't
even Christ is risen. Oh, that's true. Christ is risen. That was the kind of hard-leafed listening
after the essential.
It's a kind of card revoked.
Christ is, is it?
He truly is, is it?
Oh, you wouldn't have.
Anyway.
I got, I'm actually, didn't we're not even 30 seconds into this?
Yes, yes.
Uh, yeah, in terms of the title of the show, it was either this or, uh, how do you sell
soul to a soulless nation that sold its soul. And that has decidedly less
as some references go.
And yeah, on all displays, so people can actually read it all.
Yeah, we will just get confused.
We went with non-confusing with the current title.
Yes, so yeah, and as you mentioned, certain episodes
of this program can be slightly brain breaking.
This is probably going to be
one of them. Yeah, but back when we did the um, um,
unshewous episode about the sacrament of
function, um, in the first of the three halves of the program,
uh, we talked a little bit about the soul and some of the response we got was,
Huh?
It's, uh, exactly like that too.
We got emails that just had that one, no, no, no.
Yes, spelled the same way everyone who sent it to,
that's what was really amazing.
And so basically we're gonna take all three halves
of this episode to try to revisit that
and break that down in some more detail.
Yeah.
Cause we did and this is sort of the,
the... we'll call it the...
of a plan trilogy, even though we're stretching the definition of plan to a little there.
Yeah.
Um, any time it's used regarding me, the definition of the word plan is stretched, but,
um, uh, with our, uh, episode on the news and our episode on what is a spirit?
Hmm.
Yeah.
This is sort of the, what is a soul episode?
And so if you found those, other two I just mentioned a little brain breaking, that's
what we're talking about tonight.
Right.
out.
add this which is, you know, I like to look up etymology to see if possibly that
sheds some kind of light on what we're discussing. But the truth is that the
English word soul, it comes from Old English, it heads all the way back to a
proto-Indo-European word that literally means exactly the same thing the whole
time. Like it is a persistent word that has always meant this, which is pretty rare.
But as a result, Shed's no light on
And now the word is that you change the word time.
Yeah.
And we're even going to see that there's a, when we talk about,
for example, the Hebrew and thereby the Semitic in general
term for soul because it's, I mean, it's the same
trilateral root.
It's the same consonants in Syriac, Arabic, everything.
Yeah.
Right.
And the Greek word have a huge amount
You
overlap in their respective lexical domains. And we'll talk about it. So there's just sort of there's a word for this.
And this is it. Yeah. So we're going to start as is our want at the beginning of the book of Genesis.
And this is...
part of where we started back in the aforementioned episode where we started
talking about this a little. And this is with even though this isn't the first
time the word that's translated soul appears this is where we're gonna start
and then we're gonna back up almost immediately and pick up the previous one.
But in Genesis 2 verse 7 we read about the creation of Adam, right, the creation of
He's formed from the dust of the earth and then...
And then it says...
Sorry.
...Pregnant pause for dramatic effect.
I know! I was like, wait.
Is he like stage managing me or...
I don't know.
And suddenly, Genesis 2.7,
then the Lord God formed the man of dust from the ground
and breathed into his nostrils the breath of life.
And the man became a living creature.
living creature that's how the ESV does.
it. Yeah, and it's literally a living soul. Right. Nefesh Hayah. Right, so um,
notice the language here though. Right, the language is not what we might expect, based on the way
we typically talk about what a soul is in our culture, in that you have this body.
he made of mud, dirt, right? And then breath is breath into his nostrils, and he becomes
a living soul.
Yeah, rather than the idea of, okay, here's the soulless body, and God makes a soul and
puts it inside, which I think is the way that people tend to think of it.
Right. Right. Or they might say, well, breath, breath is spirit, right? So, right, he's breathing
the sole end.
to the body. But again, that's not how it's phrased. That's not how it's phrased.
So the soul, as we've said before, when we've just shorthand defined it, the soul is the
life of a living being. So what's really being conveyed here in Genesis 2.7 is that once
The breath of life is breathed into the body made of dirt, right?
It becomes...
alive. It becomes animated, which for
anima. Yeah, right. Just like that.
So is anima. Right. So it becomes it's
sold becomes alive. Right. He becomes alive.
So that means that when we're talking about
the soul, what we're doing is we're talking
about we have some living entity. Be it a
human or something else that is alive.
And we're talking about that life.
Right, we're talking about the life.
And while you say, right, you can't separate that out.
You can't quantify that, right?
You can't, despite many efforts in the late 19th and early 20th century,
where they would weigh bodies of dying people to see if they could determine
how much the soul weighed after.
I know.
I love that stuff.
That's not something you can separate.
and section off, right, in a scientific way, but at the same time, right, if you've,
if you've ever watched a person die, which in our modern society, a lot of people who
aren't priests haven't. But if you've ever had to put a pet down, right, if you've ever
Watch something that was alive die.
You know there's a palpable difference.
between that being the moment before and the moment after.
Yeah.
A change has taken place.
Right. The life that was there, that life is now gone.
Right.
So even though we can't scientifically quantify it, we all know this experientially.
experientially we know that it is
in some sense that the life, the soul, is a thing, but not a thing in the sense we normally
talk about in material terms.
So as we sort of briefly mentioned in passing in terms of Genesis 2.7, the Hebrew word for
Soul is nefesh.
Those three contents are shared.
in every Semitic language I know of.
That's as the word for soul.
Vowels of course are different
because words are vocalized differently
in different Semitic languages,
but the consonants are the same.
And the way it is used because words, of course,
have their meaning from usage.
Is when you survey sort of all the uses
of that term available to us,
is that
that in addition to places where it's obviously talking about life and being alive, it is
used to refer to desires and appetites.
So that idea is deeply connected here at sort of the base level from Akkadian on, it's
the languages, the idea of desiring the idea of appetite and the idea of being alive.
So.
It may not be obvious how that applies to all kinds of creatures.
We've said before on the show, everything alive has a soul, but there are different types of souls.
A tree has a soul, a dog has a soul, a human has a soul, but there are different kinds of souls.
And with a tree, right, it may not be obvious that a tree has appetites and desires, but
of course, if you study...
plants, right? If you stay them at all, you know that they do, right? Roots grow.
Ence. I mean, come on. Yeah. Roots grow toward water, right?
Right. Right. Right. And they've even done some crazy studies recently where if you play
sounds of water on a tape recorder, roots will grow toward it. Which is weird. Like, they
They don't have ears, but somehow.
Yeah.
Yeah. Right. So roots grow toward water, leaves grow toward the sun to get sunlight. Right.
So they do. Right. It's purely at the level of just nourishment, but it's there. Right. And animals,
of course, have those same kind of drives plus some additional ones. Right. So I'd be there looking
looking for nourishment, they're looking for food,
they're looking for these things, but they're also...
looking to reproduce and not only reproduce the way like plants reproduce themselves, but
animals, especially as you get higher up or more advanced animals in terms of their socialization
and social forms, they have social forms, right?
They will travel in packs.
They will have hierarchies within those packs.
They will mate for life.
They will raise their young, right?
So there are these other additional sort of desires and apatites.
as you move into the type of soul that an animal has.
And then, of course, when you get to a human,
it becomes sort of all the more complex, right,
in terms of our desires and our appetites,
and how we relate to those.
So it shouldn't totally shock us
If we learn a little Hebrew and we read...
Genesis 1 verse 20. And we yeah. I was gonna say yeah. I mean it uses the word
souls to refer to things other than people. Yes, specifically God creates all the
swarms of souls in the waters. It's referring to like fish. Yeah, is this the part
where we say that birds don't have souls or no birds do have souls.
Unless you think they are...
aren't real. Yeah, there are people unless you think the CIA has killed them all and replace
them with grunts. I think I have seen like theological arguments from Genesis 1 20 saying,
you know, because it says, right, it says this. And God said, let the water swarm with the
swarms of living souls or creatures and let birds fly above the earth across the expanse
of the heavens that they say, well, see it says, water, the waters have souls in them,
But this heavens don't.
Doesn't say souls...
birds and there's a whole argument then saying that birds don't have souls which I don't know
what the point of that is, but it's out there. I'm not kidding, I've seen this. No, I know.
As David Hume said, there is no philosophy so absurd that someone has not held it.
But yeah, yeah. And so when we're talking about a soul here to an extent, we're talking about
going beyond just the life of a living being.
Here's another angle on it. We're talking about a kind of embodied desiring.
Right, a kind of embodied desiring.
And that embodied part is important because this isn't just body in the broad sense, the way we usually use it a lot on
Lord's parents. This is body is in a biological body.
Right, biological body has a soul.
So we don't talk about
angelic beings having souls. Right. Right. Hmm. Right. Angel soul. And if someone, I don't know who
would do this, I'm certainly not going to mention his name again because I've mentioned it enough. But
if someone were to say that God is a try personal immaterial soul. Oh wow. This would be a crazy person who
who should be able to do their research on that one.
But you can-
probably guess after last episode.
So, right, so that obviously doesn't make any sense.
Christ has a human soul, but we'll get back
to that later on, though not to the person.
So, we also talked about,
we did this briefly in the episode on Aunction,
how the way in which soul and spirit
are sometimes distinguished and sometimes.
not. Yeah, because like for instance, sometimes even some of the church fathers describe humans
as being body and soul. Someone will describe them as being body, soul and spirit. Yes. And this has
triggered in a lot of circles. And this is before the internet is what's amazing to me. Because usually
this is the kind of argument that you only get on the internet. But whether which one is right.
Yeah.
humans bipartite or tripartite?
Let's fight about it.
And so that's kind of missing the point, right?
Because the truth is humans are neither bipartite
nor tripartite, they're holes, right?
And when we make these distinctions,
we're doing exactly that.
We're making distinctions in speech, right?
where we're distinguishing, for example, the body from the soul. But as we just talked about
back in Genesis 2.7 distinguishing Adam's soul from his body in the way in which those terms
are used in that verse doesn't even make sense. Yeah, because he becomes a living soul.
Right. It doesn't get a soul is not added to him. You know, it's not included in him. He becomes
of living soul. Right, and so we're distinguishing body and soul.
In speech and our primary basis for doing that is again that experiential basis of us having encountered a dead body which is a body without a soul
Yeah a body without life in it
Right and so we've labeled as soul that thing which is different between the living body and one which has died
But it's on that experiential basis that we make the distinction not that these are two separate things
stop that there's
ghost in the machine, right? Or your soul is in your skull and sort of piloting your
body around using levers, right? What was that man? What was that Eddie Murphy movie?
Was it Meet Dave? I never saw that one. Yeah, that was it. You shouldn't. Okay, good.
not only is it not meat Dave, it's not even Herman's head but anyway.
Okay.
So I did see ghost in the shell though.
The animated one may. Yeah, yeah, the okay. Okay. Yeah.
I thought I was there. You made the live action one and I was like, seriously.
Oh, yeah, that's that's right. That did come out. I never know.
Anyway, it was a disappointment apparently.
It was horrific. Um,
so, uh, yeah. So within that, right?
So that's the basis on which we distinguish between.
soul and body. Right? So what distinction is being made when someone distinguishes
between soul and spirit? Right. Right. Right. Because a lot of times this seems to be
used interchangeably. Right. Like at least in our speech we'll say, you know, that someone's
And Spirit has left their body when they die.
Right?
It just our common way of speaking.
And so really what's going on when those are distinguished
theologically, soul and spirit, is the soul is still
being treated as the life of the body.
But as we talked about in our episode about what a spirit is,
a spirit is an organizing principle of a being or of a collective.
Right.
It is sort of the consciousness right that that
level that organizes it. And so distinguishing between soul and spirit is really distinguishing
between these two aspects which we could just refer to as the soul, right? Or we could
refer to a person's spirit being that organizing principle that is of course, right, not actually
separable from their soul.
But, I mean, is it like, speak up differently?
Is it like soul?
So, functioning in a certain way, I mean, of course, again, these are just sort of like
distinctions in the mind, right?
Right.
It's sort of a power of the soul.
Okay.
Yeah.
Right.
So you've got life itself and then life as organizing principle.
Got you.
Right.
And so, yeah.
that element of the soul is also something that we know experientially.
Because if you have seen a dead body of anything that was once alive, right, doesn't have to be a human body, an animal body, right?
Even a dead plant.
What immediately happens, in addition to that change that we see where the life has gone, right?
That body also begins to break down into K.
Yeah, right when Adam died his body went back to the dust.
Ashes, ashes, dust to dust, right?
went back to the component parts
because the life leaving also took away
the organizing principle of the body.
So it disintegrates then.
Yes.
Yeah, and I mean, I think it'd be useful.
Like we might be tempted to try to analogize this to DNA,
which is encoding of course that tells everything
in the body how to grow.
and all the other things DNA does.
But I thought Noah took DNA from all the species on Earth onto his space arc.
That was Titan AE.
Oh, sorry.
Okay.
Never mind.
That was another good animated film.
Actually, I really liked Titan AE.
It had, it was a fun movie, but it also had really a really good soundtrack.
So much more not as good as the Transformers movie, but it's true.
The original one with with Daredevil.
Yes, you've got the touch, you've got the power.
Weird L. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. So I mean DNA, right? It's kind of an encoding, but it's not
It doesn't have any sort of agency or consciousness or
You know, it's it's good. Well, and also actually people didn't know it existed
Right exactly. Yeah, and then and then the other thing talking about it. Yeah, and well then the other thing is like that
The human soul as spirit
it among other things.
is not in charge of just the stuff that's definable by your DNA, but also by the other
organisms inside you that have different DNA, but nonetheless form part of your body.
You was a collective organism.
Yeah.
When you're standing there talking to someone, your gut flora is chemically communicating
with the gut flora of the person you're talking to.
You know, that doesn't feel any less gross than the first time you said that on this.
Yeah.
But just think about it next time you stand it out on this.
the big tree. Try not to. Hey, which
time.
I'll be guys. But yeah, right. So yeah, not DNA, although certain
analogy could be drawn, but it doesn't go very far. Yeah, yeah.
And so when you have other places where that distinction between soul and
spirit isn't made, right? That distinction is just not being made.
Right.
You know, it's like we can distinguish between and sometimes the fathers will do this with
they're using like the sun as an analogy for the Trinity and all analogies for the Holy
Trinity are bad analogies.
De facto.
Right.
Because you're comparing the uncreated to a created being.
They'll talk about the son.
the light of that ray and the heat of that ray. Yeah. Right. We can talk about
those separately, but those aren't like three separate things like bundled
together into a sun beam. Right. Like, like, but you could actually divide out.
had the heat. I include the light. Yes. So um
And don't come at me with this tinted windows thing, right?
Like that, you know, that's not what we're talking about.
Anyway.
So that's what's going on with that distinction.
There's another distinction that we do need to make, right?
Way back in the long ago time, in the before time,
when the grups were here.
We talked about
about the news, right? And we talked about consciousness and we talked about what that
means. And so we need to distinguish that faculty of the news from the soul, but not
the same thing. And in terms of the Hebrew Bible, in a second half, we're going to talk more
about Greek. But in the Hebrew
There's not really a word for news in Hebrew.
Does that mean that Hebrews didn't have nooses?
No, they had minds.
So but you find other words, often heart,
in other words, used to talk about the kind of thing,
kind of thing. Right.
that is spoken of in Greek through news.
And so an example where you can see that is, right back in
Deuteronomy 11 verse 13, it talks about loving the Lord with all
your heart, soul and strength.
Okay.
People familiar with the New Testament, probably already notice
something missing.
Luke 10 verse 27 adds DNA, which is what gets translated as
and the root word there with the as a preposition in front of it is a noose.
But Deuteronomy 11 has no mind.
So I guess you don't have to love God with all your mind.
You can do the other things.
Hey look, if you're mind wander.
You can make a regional series of references.
So can I?
Yeah, so brain, brain, what is brain?
Anyway.
So, so clearly
Right. And no one like argues in Luke 10 first 27, nobody like argues with Christ is like,
wait a minute, you added something, right? Because very clearly, it's talking about loving the
Lord you got with your whole person. Right. Right. And so using in Greek language, in Greek terminology,
that is part of your person, right?
And so that's why it gets included when this...
same idea as being expressed in Greek.
So if there isn't a word for it,
how is this distinction expressed
back in the Hebrew Bible?
Well, there are all of these places
in the Old Testament
and plenty more in Orthodoxy and biography,
but a lot of them in the Old Testament
where you will see the soul being addressed
It will say, oh my soul.
So who's talking?
Right.
So clearly in this picture, myself, the eye who is addressing the soul is not the soul.
Yeah.
Right. Because otherwise it would be like, I said to myself, self, right?
Right. Exactly.
Go with.
Right.
Um, so that's that was
addressed, right? And sort of exhibit A of that, right, that if you go to an
Orthodox church for matins, and you should go to matins, best services really.
In the six Psalms at the beginning, one of the Psalms we read is Psalm 103 or
Psalm 102 in the Greek numbering, which begins, bless the Lord, oh my soul.
Bless Lord, I'm so I forget not all his benefits, right?
So
This is the this unidentified speaker, right, unidentified at least in the in the text, right,
speaking to his own soul.
Okay.
And so for a little bit of news review, not to be confused with the New Zoo review, but
we talked about the news and you can go back and listen to that episode again.
We talk about how ultimately the new
is a sensory organ, that the mind has a point of attention that it can direct.
In a person can direct that point of attention at their own soul, at the life of their body,
at this embodied desiring that is within them, and speak to it.
And...
We're coming off of Great Lent and Holy Week in Paska.
Right?
If you were around for the Great Canada of St. Andrew,
all or any part of it, you heard a lot of this.
Yeah, like the Kentucky and especially, you know, my soul.
Oh, my soul.
And talking to it specifically about its desires.
Right?
its desires, its appetites.
and what it was acting upon.
And so as we talked about back in that episode,
we're talking about news, we're talking about our understanding of consciousness.
There is this older understanding, and by older I mean
in Western philosophy, shall we say, if that's
West or anything kind of a bogus game.
other than maybe Western Christianity.
And even that's iffy.
Western homes.
Westerns.
Definitely iffy.
Yeah, like what is the line between country and Western?
Right?
I mean, is that not a dotted line?
Anyway, here we got both kinds of music.
Country and Western.
Yes, soul, rock and roll, coming like a rhino.
Anyway.
Um, so.
So there's this older view, I mean, even up to Hagle who thought animals were basically
like machines, that consciousness is like a light switch, right, on off, binary thing.
So humans, the lights are on, it's like something to be a human.
Pretty much everything else lights are off.
It's not like anything.
There's no awareness.
There's no consciousness.
There's no nothing.
.
You even see this reflected in, man, we're having a heavy star trek night, right?
You go watch a measure of a man, right?
And it's, you know, is data conscious?
Yes, right.
That's like the whole debate.
Yeah.
Is he conscious?
Is he said, what does that mean?
Right?
Are you, whether the lights are on or the lights are off?
Right.
Is it like something to be him?
Well, obviously it is.
Right. This is this is one of the problems with all these arguments about AI.
Their base having now.
What happens when computers become aware when they become conscious, right?
That happened a long time ago.
Your graph and calculator had a very low level of consciousness.
Because as we talked about it at other episode,
all consciousness is consciousness is on a continuum.
Right. And it arises within any ordered system through which information is transferred.
Right. That doesn't mean it's all human consciousness.
Yeah. We're back to what is it like to be a bat?
We actually had someone on YouTube ask, is AI a spirit and becomes a soul? Maybe means it the other way.
If uploaded into a robot body.
So unless it's in a biological body, it will never be a soul.
There you go.
Unless you found a way to create something that would serve as,
would serve to give life to a biological organism,
which, right, like that's not even like a trajectory we're on.
Yeah. Yeah.
Right.
Someone else like creating a soul.
Someone else asks, uh,
is asking GPD a question the sin of
No, no, because if it were, then typing a math problem into a calculator would be divination.
Yeah, or Googling.
Yes.
It's interesting.
I mean, there's, I don't think we have enough to do a whole episode on AI, but I mean, there's been a whole lot of what I want to.
We've been interacting with for a long time, everybody, like just because there's chat GPT now doesn't mean suddenly there's AI.
Yes.
And your computer is coming.
conscious at a very low level. Right. The tectonic activity of the earth is transferring
information. The earth itself has a very low level of consciousness. Atoms have a very
low level of consciousness. They saw that in Avatar. It's not a human consciousness. Right.
We're not saying they're human. That's what everybody jumps to. Right. Like, oh,
what you're saying, like, it's got a human personality in it. Right. You don't know
it's like to be a bat, but it's like something.
Yeah.
on somebody's home, right? But that somebody isn't a human. Yeah. Right. But it experiences
the world at processes information. It has memories. It forms plans. It communicates. Right.
It's conscious. Right. There's there's a thing. And so artificial consciousness, as soon as we
started making machines that could process information, see a process information, they had some
level of consciousness. They're not biologically alive and they're not humans. And they don't
have souls. And they don't have souls because they're not biological life forms. And don't
come at me with this Picard season three stuff because that's a whole other. I still haven't
watched. Yes. And I'm not spoiling everything for Father Andrew. So thank you. Start with
that. Yeah. Thank you. I probably will watch it. But I mean, I might take away from this
though is data is conscious.
but does not have a soul.
Yes.
Okay, there's, there we go everybody.
Yes, because it's not biological,
and that's what we mean by soul.
Yeah, right?
Technically angels and demons are conscious
and don't have souls.
Solus minions of, what is it?
So this minions of something, I have to look at this.
That has to be their dotted television,
and it doesn't be, they don't have free will.
Anyway.
That's soulless minions of orthodoxy, which is a deep space nine reference.
It is a Star Trek heavy knight.
Sorry people.
It's true.
Completely unplanned, like this wasn't in the screen.
Yes, no.
And unprovoked and unwarranted, but it's happening.
So yes, so consciousness or this spectrum.
Right.
So that means that a f***.
effectively no aces, which is the property of the news, right?
Is something that exists in other forms,
in other forms of life besides humans,
but again, not in the same way, right?
So there is a unique connection and a unique type of soul.
We're gonna get into this more in the second half
that a human has, that is unique and different
as we go on again.
further and deeper into our definition of what a soul is, right? That is different than that of
any other living thing in creation. And that is for a reason, right? Because remember, humanity is
formed in the image of God. Humanity is created to continue the creative work of God, which is to put
the creation and order and fill it with life.
That includes other living things in creation. That includes animals. That includes plants.
Plants animals are linked. They also eat each other.
But we put them in order and we foster that life.
This is why, as we've talked about before, the garden is sort of the perfect image of this.
A garden is in order.
Right, it isn't good order, but that good order has
not produce sterility, rather that good order has allowed the life within the
garden to flourish. So it's that perfect combination of the two. Right? And so
when humanity is created and is sent to turn the world originally to turn the
world into a garden into paradise. Right? Part of that includes the world being
humanized.
The inhuman parts of the world being humanized by being put in order and being filled, filled
with life, plants being cultivated by humans, animals being domesticated by humans.
And through those, they are transformed.
We don't have time to go through all this here, but there are some good documentaries online
about the history of wheat.
That makes sound boring.
But go find out what wild wheat looked like before human agricultural, agriculture began
on this planet.
Well, even dogs, like dogs.
It's hard to believe that everything we call a dog is in fact the same species, but it sure
is.
I mean, St. Bernard's and Chihuahua are the same species.
And close to the same species as they can interbreed with a wolf.
Right. Right.
right? Yeah. Right, but they've been humanized. Yeah. Right through human intervention. And
that's changed them and transformed them in ways that most of us consider positive.
So the rest of creation finds its fullest connection to God through humanity, ideally.
Right
But this is also why the fact that that's how creation can find its fulfillment is through
humanity and humanity finds its fulfillment in the humanity of Christ.
That also means that when humans turn to sin and evil, right, as Adam found out, cursed
is the ground because of you, that also has effects on the rest of creation.
Right and could have the opposite effect of disorder sterility, right?
On the rest of creation due to due to our sin because we form the rest of creation after ourselves
And if we're disconnected from God then
The rest of creation will be to when we get done with it
So
if the soul is the life of a living being,
and we've talked a little bit more about soul,
but we have to also define the word life.
Right? We've defined it in terms of,
in kind of negative experiential terms.
Right? Life is that thing that is gone when something dies.
Right? But that's a negative definition,
not a positive definition.
Right. It's sort of not being dead. It's the thing you lose when something dies. But we actually
get from St. John in his gospel a handy definition of what life is. Yeah. I mean, this is from Jesus's
prayer in the Garden of Gethsemane. He says this in John 17 and 3, and this is eternal life.
that they know you the only true God and Jesus Christ whom you have sent.
Right. So there's your definition of life, right? Life is knowing God the Father and knowing Jesus Christ.
And you come to do the former through the latter, right? You come to know the Father by coming to know
Hello.
Jesus Christ. That's what life is. And so in the past, several times, I'll
read a spare, so we've referred to Saint John of Damascus's discussion of the
difference between physical death and spiritual death. Right? So he says that
physical death is the separation of the soul from the body, right? The soul
leaving the body, the life departs from the body. And spiritual death is
the separation of the soul from God. Yeah, and it's way worse. Right, way worse. But what
we see in what Christ says here in St. John's Gospel is that then there is a corresponding
distinction and connection between physical life and spiritual life. So physical life is
the connection.
Right? The union of the soul with the body. A lot of Genesis 2.7 where we started out. Right.
Right. That's physical life. And then that means that spiritual life is the connection of the soul to God.
And as we've talked about, when we talked about the distinction before, spiritual death is the real death.
physical death is the result. Is the inevitable result of spiritual death.
Yeah, and so if, excuse me, if spiritual life is the connection of the soul with God,
then you know what we see with God breathing into Adam and him becoming a living soul.
What we're seeing there is Adam becoming alive and being connected with God kind of all at the same time.
Right. Yeah. Right. It's...
the breath of God that's breathed into him.
Yeah, which is why I mean, I've seen, I can't remember who now, but I've seen some,
at least one father say, you know, man is body, soul, and Holy Spirit to kind of express
this idea about connection with God.
Yes, yeah, yeah.
And so one of our definitions then here, if this is our definition of life and if soul,
if the soul of a living being.
is the life of the living being, then the soul represents the connection to God
of a living being through which it has physical biological life. That means
everything living is connected to God. Right? Not everything living is God is
is part of God, right?
Oh, I can't...
It's not Avatar over again.
Yeah.
But it's couldn't...
connected to God. Right? And so this is why, this is why we see what we see about blood in the Bible.
Starting in Genesis 9. Right? So Genesis 9, the flood is over, Noah and his wife and his sons and their wives spill out of the ark. Right?
And God gives them permission to eat animals, to kill and eat animals for food.
Uh,
But immediately, immediately, you can eat blood or drink blood.
Yeah, he gives this proviso when he gives it permission.
Because the blood of the thing is the life of the thing and that life belongs to God.
You can't consume it.
You have to pour it out.
You have to return it to God.
The blood of sacrifices, the litigants, poured out at the base of the altar.
You can't consume it because it's the life.
And then in that same context in Genesis 9, right, right there at the same time that he's saying this
He says this applies in a unique and special way to human blood
Because humanity is made in the image of God
God, he will demand an account for every drop of human blood spill.
And he goes so far as to say not only from every person who spills human blood, but from every animal that spills human blood
He's going to demand an account
Right the lion that eats a guy is gonna have to answer to God for it is literally what the tech says
Huh, and that's a way the scriptures use to kind of take something to an extreme
Yeah, right here's how serious this is right start thinking like when will we get to see the animal judgment?
Yeah
not to be taken
literally, right? But it's that this just like at the sort of at the end of Jonah, right?
Which we heard on Holy Saturday, right? And you know, there's all these people who don't
know their right hand for their left and many cattle.
It's all this. Think of the cows, Jonah. Oh, John, not the livestock. That's, um, that's
this idea of going to it like to the extreme, right? Like, and so it's it's the same thing here, right?
That
that human life is the connection to God.
And so taking life is a very serious matter.
Amen.
All right, we're going to go ahead and take our first break
and we'll be right back with the next part
of the Lord of Spirits.
Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment.
Take your calls on the next part of the Lord of S-
give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Hi, do you know me? I'm Father Stephen D. Young.
My new book, Apocrypha and Introduction to Extra Biblical Literatures, now available.
A lot of Christians today divide ancient Jewish and Christian literature into two categories.
What's in the Bible? What's not in the Bible?
Christian East, however, has traditionally had a third category, a middle category, books
that are read privately in the home.
The Greek word for that is apocrypha.
These texts from the centuries before and the centuries after the incarnation of Christ
that go beyond even the larger canons of Orthodox and Roman Catholic churches revealed to us
the religious world and theological framework of the apostles and early church fathers.
In this book apocrypha, I survey these works which connect elements.
of liturgy, scripture, iconography,
and patristic writings.
Pamiliarity with these works will enhance
readers' understanding of the breadth and depth
of the Orthodox Christian faith.
Buy your copy of Apocrypha and
Introduction to Extra Biblical Literature
at store.anxionfaith.com
That's store.anxionfaith.com
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits,
the Father Andrew Stephen Damick
and Father Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now
At 8 by 5, two three.
That's 855 AF radio.
Well that was a lot.
I had no idea that you had done an ad read for the book.
I did that like late last night.
That's how quick the turnaround was.
Wow.
And I basically just did, I did tell you so
all this is diners club card commercial from 1987.
I recognize the intonation.
Yeah, yeah.
Who loves you?
Yeah, who loves you?
maybe. Um nice. Also the voice of Steve cut you right off on the outro. Did he
did? And all you got was Steven DeYoung will be right back. Oh, I guess I was. Yeah.
And then he changed my pronouns to they. That was that was odd. Not the doc is
pay for this episode.
That's right.
Whew.
All things will become Steve.
Yeah, pretty much.
They've already changed your name to Stephen.
I know.
I had someone at a speaking engagement give me a book and they inscribed it to Father
Stephen.
Is it something I'd like?
I'm I'm I've considered sending to you actually.
So like yeah, could you send this to him?
No.
Yeah.
So this is the second half of the show.
And we're ready to take your call so you can call us in.
if I five AF radio, if I five, two, three, seven, two, three, four, six.
And let's talk about souls.
So you get a little read out when there's a call, right?
Yeah, I do have a thing pops up on my screen.
It says it's calling.
And then has their name often wherever their phone is from, which might not be where they're
from.
And then sometimes whatever it is that they're calling about.
So that's all courtesy of...
of a truity. So yeah, so does this truity know how to spell?
What?
Yeah, I just, yeah, might be a skill she needs to develop
in the immediate future.
So yeah, right.
Yeah, we actually do have she told she just said to me, she does
know how to spell.
Okay.
She didn't spell it out.
She just told me she knows.
Good.
Does she use the Canadian spelling, though?
I don't know.
Because of you.
There's an extra kind of a Canadian accent.
Yeah.
Let's see you in there.
through the spelling as well.
But yeah, we actually do have a call coming in.
So we have Paul calling from Texas,
who has a question about the spirit as an organizing principle.
And what the relationship of that is to consciousness.
So Paul in Texas, are you there?
I am here, Father.
Welcome, Paul from Texas to Lord of Spheres podcast.
What is on your mind?
Thank you very much.
Okay.
So I had a much more in depth question,
but you all basically just demolished it with the first half.
Oh, okay.
So, no, thank you.
Thank you.
It's like how would prefer that we,
that happens.
I would prefer that we answered it rather than just demolishing.
Well, in doing so, you did answer it.
Just demolish, we can see the exceptions I had.
Does this mean we get to make demolition man references now?
Because I'm so ready for that word.
I have spent like the last four or five weeks
overlapping POSCA trying to get all of the
zoomer members
of my congregation to watch Demolition Man. It's such a fun movie. I successfully got them to watch
they live, which is an American classic. Now we're on the Demolition Man. Sorry. You probably weren't
expecting us to make Demolition. Have you seen that movie, Paul? I have not. I don't know if I'm too
young or what. I don't know what the deal is. It's from the 90s. Yeah, it's great, especially if you've
you've ever read Brave New World by Aldous Huxley.
I cannot say that I have, but I can.
So read that book first and then watch the movie because the movie is way funny or if you've read that book
It is muscular action heroes living in a soy future
Yes, so that's just alone
Sandra Bullock
Dennis Leary Wesley Snipes. Yeah, I mean what's not to love it's so fun. Yes
Okay, so sorry Paul now your actual question
Okay, so I've got...
kind of little chunks here.
The first is you said that consciousness is basically going to be a factor for any
kind of organized system.
And you discussed leaving aside the notion that you said the spirit is kind of like an
aspect of the soul and the sense that the organizing principle of it, since there can be spirits
without souls.
Does that mean that since the spirits are organizing principles and consciousness is
the fact that you're of all organized systems that consciousness is going to be present in any form of spirit.
depending on the level. Yes. Okay. Wonderful. A classic father to you. Yes.
And secondarily,
whenever we talk about the fact that you know, you also said that it's our job to organize
basically the creation. That's the fact that the job that God gave us. In a manner of speaking,
does that make us by merit of Christ's relationship with us and how he unites us with God?
organizing principle for the rest of creation and as a part of the reason that
everything is a mess could that be said in light of what you're teaching us
now as being since we're you know at war so to speak or not so to speak we are
at war with the dark powers that it's our weakness and submission willingly
unfortunately too many times with the dark spirits that it's that war of
organizing principles that then causes the you know problems with reality as we
know it.
Yes.
Yeah.
That's what we talk about.
Creation being subjected to futility through human sin.
That's what we're talking about.
Yeah.
And also that the creation groans for the revelation of the
sons of God.
Right?
So it's really that like you could also put that as the
creation is ready for its patron saints.
Oh.
Yeah.
Very not to jump too far ahead, but you are tracking with
where we're going.
Yeah.
Okay.
We permitted one final little question.
Okay. Yes. Okay. Thank you. That was it. That was no, that was the question. Like the D&D movie. Yeah.
The, the you also had made mention and I think it was in the spirit episode that we're not, you know,
our spirit. So, speak where our bodies. I definitely understand that since, you know, even our
awareness is ourselves, our aggregation of memories and everything comes from the body. We wouldn't
and have it without it.
But what, did you elaborate on that in light of the fact that...
Getting rid of the time you whine me wiggly wildly or however that order goes. I don't want to talk to you
Leaving that aside the saints are hypothetically at the throne of God without their bodies until we unite with them
And we all get resurrected together. So how do they maintain their sense of selves without their bodies if we are our bodies
By necessity and I just assuming too much of what you said by assuming what that means at all times
You have given us a perfect segue to our second half
keep listening Paul from Texas. You're tracking with us. You're tracking with us. This is good.
I definitely want to. I have to have to all, you know, played havoc with the tetra set of what I
had thought of before. I definitely wanted to make sure I was falling along. Well, yeah, we will,
we will just grab your etch a sketch and shake it violently. I was going to say you do.
This is a joke you'll get later, but you do need to learn how to use the three C shells.
three C-C-S-OK-OK.
Thank you.
Thanks for watching.
make sure you watch watch the movie we suggested. I'll read the book first. I got you. I got you. Yeah. Yeah. Okay. All right. Well, thank you very much for calling Paul. Okay. So we also have Nathan calling from the great state of Kentucky. So Nathan, are you there?
Yes, Paulers.
All right. Welcome, Nathan, the Lord of Spirits podcast. What is on your mind?
Well, this talk about, you know, this came to me with your own shooting episode that we
are our bodies and that there's not really...
like a separate self. It made me wonder, well then if you have a loved one who is hit with
like dementia or all-timers, I mean, does that mean like the person you knew and lost
is gone, like a hard drive just being wiped out?
I mean, number one, I would not say that there are, it's interesting. We talk about them
is sort of not being all there. Right. Like that's the language that we use. But I mean,
It's, it's number one, I'm not a psychologist, I'm not a doctor or anything like that.
But my understanding of the condition is that it's, it is an impairment of the way that the,
the mind, within, you know, the mind functions as it manifests itself to us, right? So that doesn't
mean that they're, that they're gone or that they're lost, you know, because still there's life in
in the body, right?
So there's still that organizing principle,
even if it's...
functioning at what might appear to us to be kind of a lower level of consciousness at
the moment. But there are still themselves, even if there's all kinds of wacky behavior
going on, or maybe sometimes almost no behavior going on, because there's all kinds of
levels of dementia. There's the kind of where you just forget stuff, and then there's
all the way to the point where you're just lying there.
I would not have like a completely different person. Yeah. Oh, yeah, sure. I mean I've known people
like I've done pastoral work with people where their dementia advances and they become very violent, for instance.
You know, and just or they start cussing a lot, whereas they would never would have any, you know, those kinds of restraints would have been in place before.
They wouldn't have done that stuff. They would not have obeyed those impulses, you know.
But I would definitely not say that their
that their soul is gone because the body is still alive. I don't know, father, you want to add her?
correct or just to me the identification of a person with their living body does
the opposite right if you are your soul and your soul is some kind of psychological
self or something that it would seem to me that that's where you're kind of
losing a person and that's also where you get arguments like Peter Singer back in
the day that unborn children and even infants aren't.
human. Yeah, right. Right. The if you are, right, embodied
desiring, if you are a living soul, you are a body that is
animated, right? That is what you are as a person. Then a
Feet is in the womb, a six month old, a three year old.
A 20-year-old, a 30-year-old, a 75-year-old, an 85-year-old with dementia is still that person.
Regardless of their ability to interact, regardless of their facility with language, regardless
of how their memory is, regardless of what they're able to articulate, what math they can
do, what abstract concepts they can comprehend, they're still a human person, and they're still
the same human person.
Right?
Just at different stages in their life, right?
But they're still the person.
So to me, this is an important distinction to make for that reason.
If the body's just a husk and the real you is this nebulous thing within, if you lose contact
with that nebulous thing within, you might be inclined to think that the person is gone.
I don't know the person is standing right there in front.
of you. That makes sense to you, Nathan? Not there, leave it out. I'll keep thinking on
I appreciate it. Okay. Sure. You want it a while. See what you can do. Yeah, it's a tough,
it's a mind bending thing because it's not how we're used to thinking. We don't tend to think
of ourselves as being bodies. You know, we tend to say, I have a body, right? Not that I am a body.
But you are.
You're a sold body.
You're a sold man.
If I may.
That was what I wanted to call the episode, by the way.
But yes, he wanted to name this episode
after one of the most racially offensive movies of the 1980s.
No, not the movie.
The song.
The song, man.
I never saw the movie.
Typical, I know.
But...
Soul man, yeah, it's a great song.
Anyway, I'm protecting you from yourself.
Thank you so much. All right. So all right. Thank you very much, Nathan for calling in
All right, rolling on okay
Yes, so bookism and plugs colors have been talked with yes apologies to fans of C Thomas owl though
If you're a fan of C Thomas owl like who even are you like what anyway, okay
Yes, so now we're going
to continue talking about souls. Now we're moving on to Greek. Greek souls. It's like a Greek
Easter. Yes. With lemon. Yeah. They're all named spiral. So the Greek word for soul,
famously, is psyche. Sometimes for nouns to English, English psyche, so where we get psychology,
etc.
um, psychic, but um, it literally,
etymologically refers to not just breath, but breath in terms of the act of breathing.
Hmm, right. And so, again, if we're defining the soul experientially,
right as that thing which is gone when something that was alive dies
one of the most obvious features if you're dealing with humans and animals is they stop breathing.
Yeah.
Which is why then, you know, we have the common expressions of someone breathing his last,
all that kind of stuff.
Right. Right.
And so that seems an obvious connection, right, in terms of why this word, this Greek word.
But the Greek word, Pseki, also includes the idea of
and desire, right? Just like we talked about the Hebrew term including kind of desire and appetite.
That idea is included also the idea of will. Now this is the concept of the natural will.
Not the way we commonly use will when we talk about free will like making choices.
We won't go down the whole St.
Maximus the Confessor Rats.
habit hole right now on that. But the natural will is something which every living being
has, which is sort of the internal push, the internal motor that directs them to continue
living and to grow and to thrive. Right? So the acorn has the same nature as the oak tree.
But
There is this internal force connected to its life, connected to its soul that causes it to sprout and bud and grow and stretch out the roots and stretch out the branches.
That's what we're talking about with the natural will.
Right. Like I will live, I will grow, I will thrive. Right. Yeah.
That kind of thing, whereas the chew, the will in terms of decision making, in terms of
making choices is.
right I'm gonna have Apple jacks instead of golden grams this morning for
breakfast right which is usually a good choice but if you get the original recipe
gold grams with the honey in the recipe yeah that might win so you don't want
the newfangled gongrams. I had paid for breakfast.
So, yeah, so it's that kind of will that we're talking about in the soul, that the soul has this sort of internal drive.
And so in Greek thought, so we're talking about Greek thought, we're talking about Greek philosophy, basically.
In Greek thought, there are these different powers of the soul.
And not everything that has a soul has all of these powers.
In fact, which powers of the
a given living creature possesses is going to determine kind of what kind of creature it is.
So at the base level, everything that has a soul, everything that's animate, everything that's
alive, has what's sometimes called the vegetative or the nutritive power of the soul, which is
basically eat, stay alive, grow, reproduce. Right. So.
And that's so plants, animals, humans, right?
All of them have this.
Then, there is the desiring part.
Usually in Greek, this is epithemia,
which is shared by animals and humans.
This is more than animal level.
That includes some of those things we talked about
in the first half, like mating for life,
caring for office.
these more advanced things, but also includes, for example, animals will eat more than they need to eat to survive.
Right, they have other kinds of desires.
They have social desires.
Other kinds of desires that they want to seek to be fulfilled beyond just eating the minimum to survive,
procreating, surviving the elements.
Right, there are sort of more advanced desires than that.
Yeah.
And then humans only in Greek thought have the noetic power of the soul.
So in Greek thought, the news is seen as a power of the soul. It is reduced to and made part of essentially the soul.
And of course, as we mentioned, only humans have an
in Greek thought.
Everything else is not conscious.
Everything else lights off, right?
Um.
in his ancient Greek thought. But because, notice the noose is folded into the soul,
which is this separate capacity in Jewish and Christian thought, is folded in Greek thought
into the soul. And so that means the soul becomes now
self-contained. The soul contains all the powers of the human. And therefore, the soul being
so self-contained can be understood as being the whole self. And so you see this reflected
especially in Plato. Yeah, yeah.
If you read the Tameas.
uh the parts of it that aren't corrupt.
Read the Tameis right play notes that now now play dough is here
because this is going to sound totally ridiculous and it is kind of ridiculous but I want to be
fair to play dough right he was like criticizing. Play dough the Tameis contains uh play dough's creation
myth essentially. Right. Is what path.
is for a creation story for him at least. But he presents it as he usually does with such things
as the likely story. Yeah right right. Right so he is not intending us to take this totally
literally. Okay so let me say that as a proviso before I say what he said. He is not intending
I guess to take this totally literally, I don't think.
So in the Tamega.
He says that when humans first come into existence they were just heads
spherical heads just a fun image
spherical heads with the soul inside
Right and the head was basically there so you'd have a skull to protect yourself and keep you from dying
I like the holders
Yes, without all the I stocks.
Um, yes.
Right.
able to float because because he says the big problem with humans just being heads is as
they were rolling around they would roll into ditches.
And get stuck places again he's not attending us to necessarily take this literally.
And therefore, they needed to develop bodies by necessity, right, to sort of carry the
head around, right? And feed themselves.
that interact with things, right, in order to keep the head alive to keep the soul in
the head, right?
But beyond, you know, the story sounding kind of goofy, right, the point he's conveying,
and it goes all through Plato's writings, and is the earmark possibly of the Platonic tradition.
Right.
is this kind of dualism where the body is a vehicle that transports the soul around.
Yeah, which, I mean, this is basically our modern conception.
Yes. You know, effectively. I mean, it's not like we, I'm sure we owe a bunch to Descartes as well, but it's still, I mean, it's basically Plato.
That's the way most people think about souls and bodies. Yeah. Yeah.
And so, um,
This is embedded even in our language in ways we don't realize.
Right, so for example the Greek word organone.
Right?
Literally means a tool or an instrument.
So, your bodily organs, right, or your body is an organ or an organism, it's your tool,
it's your instrument that you're using.
Right?
So uh...
Yeah, so this is this is Plato's view. This gets widely endorsed in the West. It's not all St.
Augustine's fault. It partially St. Augustine's fault. Beathy is way more so. Look at it, you consolation
philosophy and so even more so. So this view carries through.
And this isn't a view that gets rejected later in Western Christianity.
In fact, famously, John Calvin agreeingly quotes Plato that the body is the prison house
of the soul.
Yeah, right.
Right.
The body is the prison house of the soul.
So this carries through.
Right.
It is deeply in Western culture.
And in fact, we're even used to talking about...
sometimes even our liturgical translations unhelpfully use this language that talk about the immortal soul.
Yeah, yeah.
Right. So they'll say like that a saint attended to did not attend to the body, which is mortal,
but attended to the immortal soul. Yeah, the apolitikian, I think, for female monastics.
Yeah, and that's not a good translation.
It says it's literally not 10 to the body which dies, but to the soul which is undying,
which is not the same thing.
As immortal, right?
Yes.
So because, because immortal means does not have the property of mortality, right?
And thereby implies that unlike what we-
We clearly see in Genesis 3 and the distinction we were talking about with spiritual death
and physical death, that the soul is innately immortal and that the body is innately mortal,
neither of which is true in Genesis 3.
Yeah, all right.
In Genesis 2, Adam is created immortal because his soul is connected to God, which gives
life to his soul which gives life to his body.
body. When he is expelled from paradise, he becomes mortal. In that his soul is cut
off from God and therefore his body begins to die. So our soul is just as mortal as
our body. But what it means for a soul to die, spiritual death, and what it means for a body
to die.
Well, parallel is not identical.
Yeah, right.
So Plato, on the other hand, the soul is immortal.
Right.
No matter what.
Pre- and pre-existent, too, right?
You know, yes.
Pre-existent.
And we'll continue to exist.
It's not dependent on God's sustenance.
It's not dependent on, of course, he doesn't have, you know, the Jewish for Christian God.
Right.
It's not dependent on anything.
It is immortal.
Therefore he has read.
Yeah, right. So the soul it's born in one body, another body, another body, another body right because it's immortal.
And so for him, you know, learning is just remembering stuff.
Because in between, I was going to say the big math problem I always had with reincarnation is that there's more people now than they've ever been.
So are there new souls?
created or so there are different answers if you ask people who believe in
reincarnation yeah yeah someone think they split they split yeah which could
explain how so many people can all claim to have been yeah you know because like
a lot of people when they talk about their past lives or whatever it's
interesting how many people all claim to have been the same one past person so I
guess if you if you have the split idea then that kind of works out right right
the
The thing here is that this is the identical soul just inhabiting another body for Plato.
Yeah, right.
And in between, one body dies, right?
Soul goes off to the heavens, right, to the world of forms, the eternal world,
beholds all of these things, gets dunked in the atarussian lake, call back to an old episode,
for all you old heads out there and load of sp...
it's land. And because that dip in the lake forgets everything.
How long till my soul gets it right?
And then you're born again, right? In a new body. And over the course
you remember things. And of course Plato had an experiment to prove this,
where he took a slave boy and drew some geometric shapes in the sand. It said,
look, you can understand it. He's a slave. They're idiots.
It's...
The clearly his soul lived before.
And that's a TLDR version, but I'm not representing it.
That is what basically says.
Right.
And so, yes, the soul doesn't like Adam's soul as we saw did not pre-exist.
No, the body existed before his soulfulness.
Souls do not pre-exist.
They don't exist.
They have spheres like origin thought.
They don't exist as rough spheres the way Plato thought.
They don't pre-exist in a divine decrease somewhere.
like John Calvin thought, right? They can't. They're the life of a biological
creature, right? When at conception,
right? The a person becomes alive. There's a soul there because that being that
creature is
connected to God. Yeah, because and there are a life giving it life. Yeah. He's she life.
Right. That'll be assigned later. I guess. That was a joke. It's okay. Just clarifying.
right? So it is this connection. So this means as we talked about in the
I'm sure this episode that our life in this world is not sort of the unfolding of the identity
of our soul that already exists.
Right.
There's no freaky Friday.
Yeah.
Switch.
You know, and there's no like I need to go out and discover who I really am.
Right.
Yeah.
Or, you know, this stuff is sort of set eternally.
and then it just plays
out all like Alvin or this stuff is sort of Senator, but I discovered about myself.
Yeah. Right. I mean, and one of the big problems with this model is it basically precludes
the possibility of repentance of change of any kind. Yeah. But yeah, repentance being the worst
problem. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. It's just who I am. Well, well, change who you are. You
You got change, that's the good news, you can change.
who you are. Yes, yes, yes, because as long as you are alive, yeah. Yeah. Yeah. And so as
we said in the, um, she was episode, if you weren't you, you wouldn't be you. Right. So if
I had been born in 11th century France, I would not be father Steven D. Young, but in 11th
century France, I would be a completely different person.
Be payah it yen.
There would not be, right?
Like there would not be, there would be no commonalities.
Yeah, if you totally, for you to be able to say that that was me, right?
Right. Right.
Right. That would be a nonsensical statement that that was me.
How would it be me? Yeah. Right.
That's another person. Right.
And so the time you live, the place you live.
The experiences you have, the relationships you have with other people, all of this is what makes you you
Right the decisions you make, right?
This makes you you
The soul is not like this independently existing thing
That could have been dropped anywhere
Right could have could have been dropped into another place at another time and that would have meaningfully been you at that time
time and place. Right. And so as our colors, both kind of mentioned, right, your body is
far more related to your identity than your soul is. Souls are more alike than bodies,
if they're human souls. Right. There's been between my soul and father Andrew's soul.
right, if we can even talk about this, right, even if you could, if you could have
this in some way and observant it's a way and compare the two. Right? They're both human souls.
Right. And there's not a lot of difference. And
and this this goes against, I mean not to name names, but a pollinarianism. Right.
which of course was the ancient
in heresy still cropping up today unfortunately among certain folks that Christ did not have a human soul.
Right. The logos inhabits his body and functions in the way that a soul would function. Right.
Right. So his body is essentially inanimate. His body is just a body that's animated by
the second person of the the Holy Trinity coming and animating it or puppeting it or using it as an
instrument like right back. I'll play it out.
So, this is opposed to the Orthodox belief, which is that Christ has a human soul, he has
a perfect human soul, which represents the perfect unity.
If, as we're saying, the human soul is the connection between the human and God, then
And Christ has a perfect human soul which represents the perfect unity of humane...
with God. And that's the whole basis for our understanding of salvation. This is why St. Gregory
the Theologian says that if you believe a peleonarianism, salvation as Christians understand it is impossible.
Right. Because the human soul has not been deified then. Right. Right. We have not, the humanity has
not then connected to God in Christ.
God just showed up in a human suit.
Yeah.
Which doesn't transform humanity.
Doesn't transform human nature.
Right.
And so this...
Again, I won't name names.
So there are some, but now I get to be a little self-critical.
Now I get to talk about some Orthodox people who don't know what they're talking about.
Yeah.
You know
modern age. And I'm sure there are non-orthodox people saying the same things. So I don't think
we've quartered the market on this and it's just crept into certain folks in the Orthodox world.
In our current world of confusion about sex, gender, at all, where a lot of folks seem to not
even know the difference between the two. Occasionally you will see even these Orthodox people,
I'm sure plenty of others talk about how oh uh
The soul doesn't have gender.
The soul doesn't have biological sex.
Right?
And try to use this as some kind of argument for something.
Hmm.
In terms of gender theory, it's not even real gender theory.
It's like this weird watered down cultural thing.
Yeah, it's kind of, it's like a correct and error with another error.
Right. But here's the thing.
Uh, the answer that is, yeah.
Yes, the human souls are kind of human souls.
Right.
Because in as much as that human body is a human body, it's soul.
Yes.
Is the life of that body?
Some other body.
Part and parcel of what Genesis 1 teaches us is that because male humans and female humans
are both humans, they both have human souls.
This is not a big revelation, right?
Again, it's your body that differentiates you.
It's not that every person in the world,
how ridiculous would it be for someone to come and say?
Every one of the world has the same body,
but a completely different soul.
Yeah, well, right.
That would be absurd.
But that's just
one step beyond the absurdity of Platonism broadly constructed, which is souls are all completely,
every soul is unique and different, but bodies are interchangeable.
Yeah, which I mean, that's what we're watching work out in the culture in general now, is that
body is just so much parts they're like legos.
Right.
You know.
Right. And so yes, human souls are all the same and your biological body
Is either if you're a human
Right not an enemy if you're a human is either
Biologically male, biologically female or intersex
Yeah, and then beyond that
Gender is the social construct of in our culture. Here is how
men dress act present themselves. Here's how women dress act present themselves.
And that changes over time. The biology doesn't.
Reproduction works the same way. You don't know where babies come from. That's not my job. But
that hasn't changed. That is a trans-historical human constant where babies come from.
Biologically, right?
Um, um, the she will.
the sheer facticity.
The root facticity.
The root facticity of existence.
Yeah.
Um, so, right, our identity is not this internal thing that's eternal that we're born
with and that we later discover.
Right.
Our identity is something that is formed over the course of our life through our choices,
our experiences, our relationships externally with other people.
Right? What we do, who we love, right? The family structures, the community structures, we
become a part of and how we operate within them. That's what forms our identity. And so
the big problem with identity in our culture is that everyone is so isolated and alienated
from everyone else that they're sitting in front of their computer and they don't know
who they are because they don't have any of these roles
relationships or community structures or family or social structures.
And Aristotle made this plane a long time ago.
If you live alone, you can't be human.
If you live alone, you're either a beast or a god.
Animals can live alone.
He thought the gods could hypothetically live alone, but humans can't.
So you're either going to have to become superhuman.
Like say, say an Anthony.
It became like God out the desert or you're going to become subhuman.
And unfortunately, our culture and society is trying to grind us all down into subhumanity
by isolating and alienating us.
But the way to fight back against that, the way to understand who you are, the way to become
the person God created you to be, is to go and find it outside in relationship with other
other people in law.
shared with other people. So the your your animate body is an object of the world. And it's the subject
in all of these relationships. Right. Nobody interacts with someone else's soul. You may tell your
girlfriend, as you gaze into her eyes, that you're staring into her soul. But you know, I could see
You can see it in-
I see it. It's right there behind the left.
Wait. We're not going to hit the player, but we will hate the game on that one.
Okay. That's nonsense. Right.
Right.
And as you progress through Western philosophy, you go even beyond Plato, where, where,
right, the soul becomes sort of the thing in itself.
Right.
So rather than seeing the soul as
the connection, the active connection and relationship
between a created living thing and God,
the soul is just seen as itself sort of an object.
The sort of you, right?
And this then affects and distorts how we understand
and our first caller was already sort of leading into this,
that, that, um,
the unique nature of the human soul, the unique relationship between humanity and God.
So the language that we started using from the beginning of this show,
where we talk about the spiritual world and the material world.
And one of the things we tried to hammer home, especially in the early episodes,
is that these are not like two separate things.
Yeah, exactly.
Right, but these are overlaid. Right, these are really one thing.
together, right?
differently perceived.
Right. That's that's why I like the word unseen and seen.
Because it's, you know, there's right, it just, it's very,
it's very good shorthand for describing the fact that there is this
one world. Yes. Yeah.
Yeah. And there are scene elements and unseen elements.
Creation visible and invisible as the creed says, which is
literally a dogma of our faith.
Yeah. One creation, there's visible and invisible parts.
Right?
Yeah.
And so sometimes when people hear the orthodox language of, well, humans, right, it's at
it's said in different ways that are kind of sloppy.
It's not that they're wrong, it's just they give the wrong impression based on all of this
cultural baggage, right?
They'll say that, well, well, humans have a material part and an immaterial part.
And so they're sort of the bridge between the spiritual world and the physical world.
what that kind of makes it sound like.
If you've got a bad case of Plato brain from growing up in our culture is well, my soul is like living in the spiritual world
or at least potentially could and my body is here living in the material world.
And so you go and do DMT or something to quote unquote, enter the spiritual world, right?
Or try different meditative practices to quote unquote enter the spiritual world and leave the material world behind.
And
Right. And all of this, and this is a fundamental misconstrual of what all that means.
Right. No astral projection, everybody. Yes. Yes. Not once.
So, there's, but what we're talking about, when we talk about humans being that bridge,
it's precisely having this unique connection to God in Christ. Right. Because remember,
life is not only knowing
God the Father, but also knowing Jesus Christ whom he sent.
Yeah.
Right?
It's through Christ that this connection, right, this special human connection comes into
being.
And so it is that we are connected to God into what God is doing in the world, both the
visible and invisible creation that allows us to serve that bridge and why the
Transfiguration, the redemption of the world happens through its humanizing.
Because in Christ's humanization becomes divinization.
But we'll talk about that more in the third half.
But last note here, this is why, as we mentioned before,
in the Unction episode, bodily resurrection is so critically important to Christianity.
And why when St. Paul brought up res
like bodily resurrection and Athens,
they all laughed at him and told him to buzz off.
Yeah, it was, it's a complete joke in the pagan world.
Other than St. Dionysius and St. Herothius,
but other than them, we will hear you again.
We will hear you again.
Yeah, right? Because that was absurd to them.
Yeah.
Right? Because what does it imply?
It implies that my body is an intrinsic part of my identity,
which lies.
it's everything they believed about the soul.
Yeah, yeah.
Why would you want that back?
Right, because this Jewish conception,
this Israelite conception, this Hebrew conception,
right, second-devil Jewish Christian conception
is totally different than the Greek philosophical perspective
of what the soul is, as a self-contained,
the whole self, the person themselves,
and the body is just interchangeable, whatever.
Yeah.
Yep.
All right, well that wraps up the second half of this episode of Laura's Spirit.
We're going to take a short break and we'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Daymak and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment.
Take your calls on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF Radio.
Hi, I'm author Sarah Bern Martelli and I'm thrilled to announce the release of my new book,
Memory Eternal, Living with grief as Orthodox Christians.
Losing someone we love is never easy, but the Orthodox Church provides a wealth of resources
that help us to bear it.
I draw on these theological, scriptural, and liturgical resources as well as the collected
experience of a variety of people undergoing grief and loss.
to provide a kind of road map to the grieving process.
I also include an eight-week bereavement curriculum
that can be used in a group or on one's own.
As Orthodox Christians, we do not seek to get over grief,
but to carry the memory of our loved ones
eternally in our hearts.
Memory Eternal is now available in paperback, e-book,
and audiobook at store.angentfaith.com.
that store.Ancient Faith.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Thanks, boys and Steve.
Got it right this time.
I appreciate that.
You grew your bone.
Indeed.
video of a car but...
Before we take you, Collar, I just want to mention that we are still selling tickets for the
Lord of Spirits conference to be held at the end of October at the Antioch In Village in
Ligonier, Pennsylvania. You can go to store.antitvade.com slash events and get your tickets. There's only,
I think, I don't know, a couple dozen spots left. Like we're looking at close to 250 people coming.
It's pretty great. And there are now, there are cabins because we've sold out the Antioch In Village
conference center.
completely. But now you can actually get cabins at the camp, which is right next to the conference
center. And you can fit eight people in each one of those cabins. It's much cheaper, but it's not
quite the level of amenities that you would get down at the conference center or some other hotel
or whatever, but it is a very cheap option for lodging. So again, it's stored at nichemfaith.com,
slash events. It's going to be a whole whole lot of fun. Come the end of October. I fully expect
at least one person in a bat costume. I'm not telling anybody to do that, but pretty sure it's going
to happen. Let me just say if you do get one of these last tickets and you decide to stay in one of
the cabins and when you get to the cabin you find like a really weird gross looking leather bound book
at a real to real tape recorder do not play the tape. Good advice for life. I'm just saying it's all.
and father Steven
the young. Don't play the tape. We will have a lot of clergy on site for exorcisms, but
still we want this to just be a fun cool weekend. Don't play it forward. Definitely. Don't
play it backwards. Yeah. We don't need all that hassle. Yeah. Yeah. All right. So we do
have a caller. So we've got our friend Samuel from Virginia. God's God's chosen country.
Calling and so Samuel, are you there? Yeah, I'm there, brother.
Welcome.
back to the Spirit's podcast, Samuel from Virginia. What is on your mind?
Well, when I was hearing you talk about the human soul being a unique thing, I was
wondering how that relates to man being created in the image of God.
Yeah, I mean, it's a good question. So, like, I think one particular element of us, as we've
talked about the image of God many times before on the podcast, is that we are images of God.
Right, and so the human soul is that connection to God. I mean, everything that has a soul is connected to God,
but we're connected to God in a unique way, in a human way.
And we image God in the world in a way that everything else doesn't.
Right, so that is at least the connection that I would immediately make.
Pun fully intended. Father, I don't know what would you add to that or expand outwards?
Yeah, well, and that of course is grounded ultimately in
in Christ, right? And in the union of our shared humanity with God in Christ, and what
that means for humanity, right? Christ did not become incarnate as any other kind of creature,
or otherwise. And so we tend to
This is this is the the the thing from an ecumenical counsel that I find we talk about the least
Calcedan said that
Christ is according to his
divine nature
Consubstantial with the father and the spirit and according to his humanity
Consubstantial with us right and
even though
or Christology is
very clear about this, there still tends to be a mode of thinking when it comes to the
incarnation that God became a man.
Right?
Yes.
It was with our concept of individual and individual human person.
And not that Christ represents the union of humanity that we share with God.
especially when we're
talking about the human soul. And also when we're talking about the image of God, because
this is where the the wibbly wobbly time you, why me stuff comes in, right? If you look
at it, at I kind of the creation of Adam, the way him being created in the image of God is
expressed in our iconography is that you have Christ there shaping his body and he looks
like Jesus. Yeah, yeah, yeah. Right. That's sort of our our iconographic way of expressing that.
Right.
And so from the get go, there's this unique connection
and therefore a uniqueness to the human soul
and connection to God beyond other living creature
that is part and parcel of that imaging.
Does that make sense, Samuel?
And it makes sense.
All right, well thank you very much for calling
and we'll probably talk to you again in the future.
I'm sure because you already repeat call it
Yeah, Christ is risen. He truly is.
All right. I don't care what you say. I'm going to say indeed, he is risen.
You can say indeed. It's fine. It's not the most euphonious way of saying it in English,
but it's okay. It's all right. I'm not going to correct anybody.
But we actually... Well, yeah.
And speaking of repeat collars, we actually have Paul from Texas calling back
with another yeah is that you it's you again Paul is it?
Yes it is and God bless you and I believe it was
sure to let me back on.
You are I think the only person who is called twice in a single
episode.
What can you make in landmark?
Did you put out a hat in sunglasses before you called
coincidentally perhaps.
Okay, a little plastic mustache.
Yeah.
You just you guys moved on to a new topic and then I was like, oh, no,
question and I try my luck.
Okay, have you watched Emission Man since we talked to you last?
I haven't. I have not found the time. I apologize, father.
All right. Well, okay. We'll get on it.
I thought it'd be a problem.
Okay. So my question is that you got into detail talking about the idea of
the will and especially kind of detailing the difference between like the very,
very basic life form kind of will that even bacteria might have for, you know,
eating and whatnot.
propagating and then the difference between the higher version of the wheel which granted is not necessarily a loan to us
but of course ours of a much higher magnitude.
Now I was hoping that I this is probably because I still have a very rudimentary understanding of the argument,
but I was hoping you might elaborate at least a little bit as long as it doesn't get too off from the show of
how that relates to the
the dispute between the orientals and the Orthodox Orthodox about Christ.
one will both divine and man or two wills, one divine and one man.
Right. That's going to really endear you to them
referring to that as the orientals and us as the orthodox orthodox.
But you may not be worried about that.
You're our median friend will not be buying you a beer next week.
Yeah.
I'm sorry, all of you out there.
Yeah, well, okay.
I don't know, correct me if I get this wrong, Father, but I think you might be mixing up
terms a little bit from what we were talking about.
So we were talking about he's not okay.
We were talking about different kinds of souls, but there's also Will, right?
Yeah.
And it's not totally off topic.
No, I mean, it's, yeah.
I mean, Will is the sorry to preemptively, I'm actually you like.
No, it's okay.
I mean, Will is a thing becoming what it is.
You know, right the internal right and so this is
Understanding the natural will this is why it comes up in St. Maxima's the confessor
Right is is because he's dealing with what the issues surrounding what's going to be the six-seq medical counsel
Uh, which is gonna establish that Christ has two wills. So why he's talking about the natural will the nomencl we will go again all the way down that rabbit
But so sort of the paradigmatic point in scripture for this is Christ in the Garden of guess emity
Great.
when he says to his father, not my will, but yours be done.
Right? If it be your will, take this cup for me,
but not my will, but your will be done.
What's going on here?
Right?
And the natural will that we were talking about,
this quality of the soul, this drive,
is exactly why we say Christ had two wills.
So Christ's human soul, which is a faculty
quality of his human nature.
has a human natural will, which human natural will is the drive to live, right?
To survive, right? To not die, right? Especially not die a horrible death, right? And that's not bad.
That's not evil, right? That's a good thing. It's normal to tell you know he's human. Right?
one of the way. And so this is taking
his evidence. He Christ has a human natural will. He does not like desire. He has this intro to
live, to not die. Right? But, right? Well, he has that, right? He also shares the divine will with
the father, which was to die. Right? And so this is not, we do not mean. Sometimes people think when
when we say that Christ has two wills, we're saying,
like he had two different minds or two different consciousnesses
like a human one and a divine one, right?
And that's not what we're saying, right?
The Holy Trinity shares one will
because they share one nature.
It's what we're saying is that there is within him
as a human having a human soul a human will,
which caused him to grow to adulthood physically, right?
two, three.
human physical adulthood and to eat and these other things, right? And that's not bad, but that
when the time came where, right, that natural good human will to do that needed to be subjected
to the divine will, which was to lay down his life voluntarily, then that is what he did.
Yeah.
Yeah, yeah.
which is a perfect example of obedience as a son,
but it's reminiscent of,
in my maybe I'm just stepping here
above the fail tocaues when she first said,
let it be said, done to me as you said.
Sure.
Because like we talked about in the first half,
your news can talk to your will or to your soul.
I mean, and will is a power of the soul.
So you can look at your soul.
You can look at the things that your soul is desiring.
Right.
The fact...
it's a natural will doesn't mean you're a slave to it. Right? You can talk to it, you
can restrain it, you can control it, you can guide it. Right? Which is part of the what
morality is. And this kind of feeds into the notion of us growing as a race and as individuals
kind of like when Paul talks about both the law and as the angels correct how they kind
of their over us as teachers until we reach a certain point.
Right, right. So you can sit there and your natural will is saying,
eat the whole tray of brownies, right?
But your higher function says, no, your wife baked these brownies.
She wants some of the brownies.
And so you restrain yourself.
You eat only most of the brownies.
Kind of truly.
Well, I appreciate it. Thank you very much, fathers.
and as an
for giving me for forgetting this, but Christ is risen.
He is risen.
God bless. Thank you.
Okay. We're going to take one more caller.
We have a guy named Steven from California calling in.
And I think he's got a bit of a mind twister.
So Steven, are you there?
Yes.
Can we call you Bruce so it doesn't get confusing?
Yes, I'm sorry.
High-speed.
Okay.
Anyway, my question is in regards to the body's soul dynamic that you're talking about.
So once you're dead and you've been in the ground for long enough, your body kind of goes
away and becomes like some other thing, like maybe a peat and buy a...
becomes like brass and then the whole circle of life thing.
So after everybody's resurrected, how would that resurrected body be you if it's not the
same stuff that makes up the you that is currently you?
If that makes sense.
Yeah.
We're tempted to just say, listen to the body episodes from way, way back.
But I mean, just briefly, right, a body is not the stuff, right?
It's not reducible to the stuff.
And the reason why that's the case is because, for instance, that most of the stuff that
currently constitutes your body is not the same stuff that it's always been there.
Right?
You've traded out a lot of stuff over time and yet you're still you, right?
So it's not about the parts.
about the atoms, the molecules, whatever.
a body is the collection of all of these things together.
It's not you are not the sum of your materiality.
So it doesn't matter that your atoms and molecules are going to get traded out.
It doesn't matter that a king can make a progress to the guts of a beggar.
That stuff doesn't matter.
What matters is that you as your body are more than that.
there's something going on there that's...
part of what the soul is, right? It's the life of all of that together. So yeah, you don't lose
consciousness by your, you know, your corpse decaying, and you don't become a completely other person
in the resurrection. You're still you, although you are a different person in the sense that
your body has been transformed, you know, it's like the St. Paul says that the resurrected body is
Almost you know
the relationship of a plant to a seed, you know,
sewn in corruption, raised in in corruption.
So there's gonna be a big difference.
We don't know exactly what the difference is gonna look like,
although it's gonna be maybe sort of angelic on some level.
But, you know, it's still you, you're still you, right?
There's a persistent you in the midst of all of that.
I don't know if all you wanna add
or anything to that or correct whatever.
Yeah, I think it's like every seven years, right?
that all the matter in your body.
changes out or a lot of it. I'm not sure that all of it does, but a lot of it for sure.
Right, almost all whenever, right? Like sluffs and shifts and like, yeah. I mean, when I see Madonna
shamble out on stage recently, right? Like I still believe it's Madonna. It doesn't look like her,
and I don't think there's any original parts, but still her. Yeah. I think she's the modern day
a ship of thesis. That's real.
So howstuffworks.com says that the body replaces cell types every seven to ten years with
the exception of neurons in the cerebral cortex, which stay from birth to death, apparently.
So you're tiny little bit that you're carrying around the whole time, but the whole rest
of you.
Most of it's not, yeah, most of it's not.
So does that help?
Stephen and Bruce, sorry, Bruce.
a little bit. So does that mean?
but there's an immaterial version of your body
that stays behind even after the material stuff is gone
or does your soul record the aspects of your body
that makes you, you after your physical body is gone?
Hello?
That's out of father Andrew Punting on that.
Yeah, I don't know how to answer that.
I don't know.
That's...
You have, so I mean, you, you, you like the saints are embodied.
Right? Yeah. And we're going to get into that this half.
Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
Okay. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
That's your track. Yeah.
You're track. But, but the other element to this is that in terms of what our resurrection
body is like, right? Our touch point is Christ's body.
and it sort of helps and doesn't help at the same time, right?
It helps in the sense that we can make certain points, right?
Like St. Thomas could touch him.
The wounds are still there, right?
Because Thomas can, he says,
handle me and see,
spirit has not flesh and blood,
or flesh and bones, sorry, as you see that I have.
From which some people conclude Jesus had no blood,
which is just amazing to me, but anyway.
I know.
At least he, as far as not flesh and bones,
as you see that I have, right?
So he was,
there's some kind of materiality in tactile thing,
at the same time he could sort of appear with the doors being shut and locked in the midst of his disciples.
Yeah, so there's something different going on there, but we don't know exactly how it is.
Body can be everywhere on Sunday morning, right?
So, I mean, that's why I say it helps that it doesn't help.
Right? It's, it's, um, so we can see that there are ways in which the way we normally think about particle physics, don't
to the resurrection body, but we can also see that it's not utterly immaterial, right?
That there's distinction there.
Okay.
Yeah.
All right.
Well, I hope that helps Bruce and we are going to get into that more as we go through this
half.
All right.
Well, I'll be looking forward to it.
Thank you.
All right.
It's always nice to hear from the philosophy department of the University of
while I'm alone.
Yes. Okay. All right. Part three. A third half because it's a show and a half everybody. So all
of that said, what is eternal life? Yes. That's what he's said. To know the, yes. So yeah,
we're back to where we started. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. With the St. John's Gospel, right? So we need to kind
of change our thinking.
about what eternal life means.
And here's what I mean.
Right?
Because scripture speaks about it very differently.
The father's understand it very differently.
Then we typically do.
Because for us, we typically understand eternal life
in a quantitative way,
rather than in a qualitative way.
Meaning it'll live forever.
Who wants to live forever?
Right.
We think...
that eternal life means there's sort of this endless succession of moments into the future
and they're all going to be pleasant, right?
That's sort of...
Right.
And that time and space and everything will basically be exactly...
Experience exactly the way it is now just without all the bad stuff and it'll never stop.
Whereas in scripture in the father's eternal life is a qual-
qualitative issue. It's a tight kind of life, right? It's a kind of life, not just an extent.
Right. And for those of you who may have watched the good place, now back of the day,
it's not been off the air for a while. So this is without finding the correct Christian answer,
Right?
The sh-
show kind of found the flaw in this kind of cultural view of
eternal life. Yeah, I mean, the way the way it depicts it, even
for people who can get to quote unquote, go to heaven, is that
it's just this endless series of pleasing experiences you can
do whatever you want. And eventually what happens at the end
of the show is the main characters all get bored of it, basically.
and they step through a hole into a blue.
So it is well maybe oblivion nobody knows what's on the other side. Yeah, it's yeah, they're just they're gone. Yeah, so I have a I have a film theory about the whole show. Oh, by the way, really my film theory about the whole show is they are never in the bad place or the good place they're in purgatory the whole time. Oh, okay.
Rewatch it and think.
All right.
Um.
That's.
Everybody, watch your Dante.
It's when they're done in purgatory.
they go through the gateway and that's when they actually go to heaven.
But yeah, that reveals the flaw because it would.
Right?
Like, I mean, if your view is I get to eat ice cream for every meal, my favorite flavor.
Endlessly, right?
Yeah.
That's right.
It's not a turtle light.
That's not what we're talking about.
Right?
And so it's a qualitative issue.
We don't know how, we've talked about this before, of course,
time and space don't exist.
Right?
What we call time and space, those are factors of our human experience.
Of our current embodied human experience.
Right?
because we're just talking about the example with Christ.
resurrection body, clearly kind of experiences space differently. No, he's God, so I mean,
we can't even fathom it, but even from the perspective of his human body, he is able
to go from one place to another without traversing the space in between, which includes locked
doors. Yeah. And it doesn't take him time to do that. Right.
So, whatever our experience of time and space is going to be like in the life of the world
to come, or even if we're just talking about the intermediate state in between, right?
Again, with the intermediate state, which is what we call that period of time between
when we die physically and the bodily resurrection of the whole creation, are we going to experience
time.
We tend to have this cultural view that like you're in heaven or in hell or in Hades kind of like waiting like it's like the waiting room and you're either in the good waiting room or the bad waiting room.
I can tell you for sure it ain't like that right we don't know exactly what it's going to be like right but.
but how exactly does that work?
Right, we don't know.
But there's a very important verse, a couple of verses.
actually in terms of this, in terms of what eternal life is, in St. John's Gospel that we read
back on Lazarus Saturday morning. Yeah, I mean, this is weeks ago. It's really intriguing. It's a
really intriguing little exchange between the Lord and Martha, you know, where he says to her,
your brother Lazarus will.
live again. But yeah, he goes on to say this, this is John chapter 11 verses 25 and 26.
Jesus said to her, I am the resurrection and the life. Whoever believes in me, though he die,
yet shall he live. And everyone who lives and believes in me shall never die. Do you believe this?
So yeah, there's a little parsing we can do to kind of...
Yeah, yeah, because a lot of it less of a riddle.
And especially when we're reading big chunks of St. John's Gospel,
like the first Gospel reading at the 12 Passion Gospels at Holy Week, right?
Like, it's easy to just see this as like, okay, a thousand deep theological riddles just whisked past me, right?
Like because there's so much of this that so, you have to break it down so much, right?
So yeah, Martha had come out to see Jesus.
Jesus asked
that tells that Lazarus will rise from the dead. He'll be part of the resurrection.
And Martha says, yes, he'll be raised up on the last day. So she believes it like the bodily
resurrection at the end of time. But this is then Jesus' response to her.
right? Is that he's not talking about the end the end of days. He's not talking about the last judgment.
and that final resurrection. Right? Yeah, he's talking about the first resurrection. Yeah, he says I am the resurrection
Jesus is the resurrection
And of course it's translated believes in this is more like his faithful to right whoever is faithful to me
Right, and it says though he die yet shall he live
Well pod just leave that for a second then he immediately says and everyone who lives and believes in or is faithful to me
she'll never die.
So that just sounds like he contradicted himself, right?
Yeah, though he died yet she'd have lived, so it leaves him, he shall never die.
Yeah, he just said, well, wait, though he died, he won't die.
What, what?
Right?
And so this is a place where that understanding of the difference between physical and spiritual
death becomes critically important, right?
what Christ is saying here is that whoever is faithful to me, though he f-
physically die, yet shall he live spiritually. And everyone who lives and is faithful to me,
shall never die spiritually."
Yes. So in other words, whoever is faithful to him, even though his soul is going to separate
from his body, yet his soul will remain connected to God and not be separated from God in Christ.
Yeah. Yes.
And that's why he says that he is the resurrection in the life because it is through him.
It is in Christ that that person's soul remains connected to God,
though it be separated from his body.
And so we have to come back to an understanding of the term magnanimity, big magnanimous.
This means something totally different.
now. Right. Yeah. Now it means, you know, you're basically generous. Yeah. Yeah. Um, but
if you break down the Latin again,
animus soul, animus, big,
magnanimus, being great sold, having a big soul. Right. And this is part of our understanding of
of the same.
in this life, that in this life already,
they're already experiencing eternal life because their connection to God
is already great, it's already big, it's already deep,
whatever adjective we want to use to describe it,
however you want to picture it.
And that means this is the connection, this is the conduit,
I can't do it. This is...
through which God gives life to them, including their body,
because again, that's who they are.
So it gives life to the body.
The connection to God gives life to the body.
And so this is why their st.hood in this life
is expressed not only through, it is expressed
through what we might call now moral behavior,
through the fruits of the spirit being manifest.
life being manacist and fruit being manacist abundantly.
And that includes the moral aspect.
But also, right, read sometime how long these non-martered saints lived in the
cynics are in.
Yeah, a lot of them.
A lot lived to over a hundred.
Yeah, great old age.
This is also why we have in corrupt relics of saints, right?
and Saints whose relics give off fragrances of plants.
and flowers and life, even though they're relics. It's a quote-unquote dead body, right? But the body still
has this. Go back to our Relics episode. And so that connection to God is not broken by physical death.
When that state eventually does physically die, that does not have a
negative effect that does not cut him off or her off from God.
Or from us. Right. Through Christ. Yes, they are in Christ. Yeah, if we're all in Christ,
like why would why is dad a problem? Right. This is why Christ says regarding Abraham,
Isaac and Jacob. God is not the God of the dead, but of the living. And he says that as a proof
of the resurrection. Yeah, right, right.
the Sadducees. The Sadducees, the resurrection, the Sadducees,
denied is the one that Martha believed in. But when Christ wants to
demonstrate the reality of the resurrection, he talks about somebody who died
2000 years before, as still being living. Why? Still connected to God.
Right? And also, right? And that may poke at some of our Protestant friends
a little bit.
who object to us seeing the prayers of saints, etc. because they say they're dead, right?
Of course they're not.
Now we have to poke a little at our Roman Catholic friends with the Biotific Vision and all,
right, that that that connection is also not broken or negatively affected by the eventual bodily resurrection.
In fact, it's deepened by the bodily resurrection.
The bodily resurrection will be greeted as a good and beautiful and wonderful thing to
be in the body again.
Sorry, Plato.
Right?
That is superior.
The communion with God in the body is superior to that experienced in the intermediate
state.
Yeah, the post-death pre-resurrection state.
Yeah.
Right. Now the negative side of this, this also tells us that everything we've just said
about eternal life also reveals to us something about what is meant by the imagery used in
the scriptures regarding eternal death.
Yeah, of which there's a bunch of different imagery, you know, but yeah.
Yeah, and this is one piece of it.
And you sometimes get folks who the theological term for this is annihilationism where they say,
well, okay, so where do bad folks go when they die?
You know what I have in, when the angels fly.
They say they just, well, see, look, it says eternal death.
So that means they just die.
They just cease to exist.
And then they, you know, that's it.
They're gone.
Yeah, but that's not what death is.
Death is not nonexistent.
.
Right, that's not what happens to you when you die.
You don't see to exist.
Right.
When you physically die, you're so separated from your body.
So eternal death, like eternal life, eternal life,
is talking about the quality of spiritual life,
the deepness and richness of the connection to God.
Eternal death, therefore, unfortunately,
is an image of being cut off from the source of life,
be cut off from God.
It's a subhuman state.
Right, because just as, and the father's used this language,
just as this quality of eternal life,
this quality of the human soul is unique to humans.
For that to be fully realized is to become truly human.
To become fully human.
Therefore, the opposite being cut off from God
as the source of life is to cease in some sense to be human
for humanity to be diminished.
And may this happen to no one, but the scriptures hold it forth as a possibility to be avoided
and a horrible one.
So that was the first half of our third half.
Now we have a second half of the third half.
It's a lot of halves.
There's a bunch of people whose brains aren't breaking over the soul stuff, but this half
language is just triggering them unbalancing now.
Um, in that ever green too, people come back like, how come they say there's three halves?
Just great.
Welcome new listener.
Yeah.
So, so now we are going to talk about what it means to become a spirit.
I mean, you get this language in Psalm 104, which then gets echoed in Hebrews one where it
says about God, he makes his angels spirits.
which makes his angel spirits, which is interesting language.
It's not that he created them as spirits,
or he created spirits and he called the angels.
Those things are true, but there's something more happening there.
Right. So, yeah, we think angelic beings,
well, wait, they are spirits.
How could he make them to be spirits?
Well
In the first place angelic beings are finite beings.
Right.
They're vast cosmic intelligences, but they're not infinite.
They're finite in a way different from our finitude, but still finite.
Right.
Because they're created beings.
Right. Unlike God.
God is the only infinite.
Right.
And so it's a different kind of finitude, right?
and say, job to math.
says that God alone knows their limitations, right? They are obvious to us because right now at
least we're below them, right? So we compare them to our own limitations and they seem virtually
limitless, but from God's perspective, they're limited, right? And he understands their limits because
he put them there when he created them. But as we talked about in our episodes about what episode
about what a spirit is, spirits are these organizing principles of larger collective...
creative, created realities. We talked about this, that a spirit is this organizing principle
for at a higher level of consciousness, that it is individual being, this organizing principle
for a collective. And it's not immediately obvious how a finite being can do that.
Yeah.
Right?
Like, I mean, we could think about like, you know, a general or a king, right, who is,
of course, a finite being, and he gives orders to other beings, right?
But the general is not like the consciousness of his army.
Right.
And the king does not represent in himself the consciousness of all his people, right?
So it's easy.
counterintuitive that a finite being could be that, right? Unless, of course, as the
Solomon Hebrew says, God makes that finite being to be the consciousness, the organizing
principle of a larger reality.
Yeah, he's sharing his ministry with that being right his governance of creation
Right
He is sharing it, and that is how he is sharing it.
He's not making him like the vice-roy where God gives him orders,
and then he passes those orders on.
That's external.
This is different than that.
Well, in the same way, if we understand this with angels,
a human person is likewise a finite being.
With a soul as the organizing principle of himself,
Right, the sole functions.
as the spirit is the organizing principle of the human person.
That soul is connected to God in Christ,
who is the logos.
As the logos is the organizing principle of everything,
the whole creation.
And so as we quoted in St. John's Gospel,
knowing God involves knowing Jesus Christ,
whom he sent.
And so in a parallel way to the angels,
through this connection of their soul to God in Christ.
The saints are made organizing principles for larger collective realities,
through being in Christ.
And so this is what lies behind the language of the saints and glory being equal to the angels,
of their governing. It's not this external governing.
Right, and equal to the angels is not just status.
It's a role and a function in activity.
Right?
And so in a sense, the saints have a body that's a greater body, right?
The material human body, right, which they will have again, right, at the resurrection.
But this is also what's behind and this is probably the, I mean, I was going to say it's
the best place to understand this.
This is...
a brain-breaking part that's hard to wrap our heads around, right? Because we're finite humans.
But a place to see this, a way at this, at least, is the idea of heavenly patronage,
both of individual people and collectively. So think about St John the Forerunner
and the way in which the prophet Elijah's life became the ordering principle for his life
And why St. Luke says he came.
in the spirit and power of Elijah.
Right, yeah, it's not just a metaphor.
Right, it's not just a metaphor,
it's not just external imitation.
Right, there's an actual direct relationship there.
Right, that is formative.
And what's true there with an individual
with a patron saint is also true
with churches, nations, organizations,
any other collective group that takes a
spiritual patron
Right that spiritual patron that they take
is going to
then be transformative and become the organizing principal for
the life of that collective group or unit
And this is also then of course.
Siniquan non of this is the Holy Spirit who when he comes into us, right, unless we're grieving the Holy Spirit
Will become the organizing principle for our life the ultimate one
Right as we become like God
Yeah
Yeah, so to wrap up
You know one of the questions that
Comes up a lot just in Christian life and parish life
live.
And I think this is a question that maybe kids ask more than adults,
but I wish adults would ask a little bit more.
And that's this question of what is heaven like?
What does it mean to be saved ultimately?
That ultimately is the same question.
And our minds, I think, because especially for those of us
who grew up here in the United States, things we see on TV,
You're going to be in the next video.
our image of what heaven is like probably defaults in many cases the kind of
cartoonish thing with people sitting around on clouds and playing
harps. And of course that's that's not it, right? But then also we might get a
little bit higher and sort of see this kind of ethereal again cloud world with
golden gates standing there and you know all that kind of stuff.
And I mean, I've had people tell me that they think that heaven sounds boring, that it sounds
really, really dull.
And it's usually because the imagination of it is something even less than what we saw
in the good place, even less complex than that, less interesting than that.
And one of my favorite expressions for...
what exactly it'll be like, which again we don't totally know. We know some
things that we can talk about some things that have been said in Scripture
things that have been said by the saints and so forth. But one of my favorites
of course comes from one of my favorite writers and that's you know JR Tolkien
where in one of his letters to one of his sons he has this to say he says there is
You
place called heaven, where the good here unfinished is completed, and where the stories
unwritten and the hopes unfulfilled are continued. They may laugh together yet," he says.
And while I don't think that that encapsulates, and it's not a sort of a, I would not describe
it as a dogmatic definition of what the life of the age to come is like, I like it a lot
because what it does is it helps us to see
that the beauty and the good and all of those things that we love in this life that seem to be
unfulfilled because of the imperfections of this life, because of the reality of what life in
this world is actually about, that that is going to be fulfilled, completed, and especially I like the word
continued. He talks about stories unwritten are continued. And...
One of the reasons why I think that that's so beautiful aside from just giving us an anchor from our own experience that we have now in order to try to imagine.
What it's going to be like is that also it's an image that the life of the age to come is a creative life.
that it is not simply this static thing, right?
Now time is gonna work differently for us.
We're gonna experience it.
differently than we do now for sure. So we don't, what will motion without time look like?
I don't know or whatever, you know. I don't know. But nonetheless, the idea that the life
the age to come is going to be a creative life and a constructive life. However, that can be
construed, I think is a very beautiful and hopeful thing. I heard someone one time react to some
some of the stuff we've said on this show and see.
Like, life of the age to come is basically...
becoming middle management?
Like, well, no, because it's not like an earthly bureaucracy, right?
Where all of that is really just super dull.
It's not like that at all.
It's instead, it's an invigorating, energizing, creative,
interesting existence.
And again, we don't know exactly what it will look like.
I probably said that 10 times now.
but we do know that the scenes
who are experiencing it as a foretaste now
or depending how you understand time,
they're experiencing it fully now,
that they are joyful.
They're not showing up in dull suits and saying,
oh yes, I had to check 27,000 files just this morning.
That's not their experience.
And it's also not showing up with robes and harps and stuff.
Although, you know, a harp can be a beautiful...
image of creativity and all kinds of wonderful things.
But, yeah, so as we conceive of the soul and try to get our heads around it as much as we can,
I think that seeing the destiny in Christ of the soul, of the life of the body as being a truly lively life,
that it is truly an energizing, energized creative life.
puts a frame around what we're trying to accomplish as Christians that I think is really beautiful
and hopeful and gives us a lot to fix our eyes on and strive towards, you know, that in Christ,
that this is where we're going, that we can become all love, you know. What an amazing,
even just thought to have you
even if we don't quite understand the reality yet.
Well, Stephen.
Be careful there.
You don't want to pick,
tick off the harpists.
I know, it's harpers.
They're almost as bad as the flautists.
They'll really eat your lunch if they come after you.
So, yeah, you mentioned this middle management thing.
the envy.
sort of externality with which we view this idea of gods,
dominion over creation ultimately and then the angelic beings and the saints.
We're going to participate in that but as we talked about tonight it's much more
intimate and direct and deep than that.
that end.
As we've said a lot on the show, there's not sort of neutral ground to stand on.
We talked about also in the second half identity and part of the problem with taking this
kind of quasi platonic approach of identity being something innate.
in me that I discern is that when people go to seek their identity and they don't realize
that this identity is something that's going to be found outside themselves in relationships,
not just with other humans but with other spiritual powers, be it the Holy Spirit, being it some
other spirit is that they are very quickly led into certain.
traps because just like material nature, spiritual nature,
or pores of acu.
There are plenty of powers and principalities out there
that would love to get their hooks in you and form you and become the organizing principle of
your life. Probably the biggest one in our culture here in the US and I imagine in most
of the Anglophone.
world that would be listening to us is Maman, the pursuit of, and Maman, their
maquard includes not just money, right? It includes that wealth, but it also includes
the concept of reputation. And that may be, in our very contemporary world, the world
of social media, the world of instant and weird celebrity where people are just
famous.
famous for doing anything, just famous. That desire for clout, for influence, for celebrity,
maybe even the more powerful of the drives connected to MAM and even more powerful that
the drive to get money. That's certainly around two.
These competing things will very quickly seize hold of us, reorganize our life, reorganize
are very identity are sent.
of ourself, our sense of who we are. And begin to transform us, as we said, in this life
already into something less than human, into something less than what God created us
as and created us to be. And that is a progressive thing. It is a progressive thing. And if we aren't
deliberate about.
becoming the person who God created us to be,
then we will 100% fall into that.
It takes work to be a Christian.
It takes hard effort, it takes determination.
I tell people all the time,
if you're trying to decide what to do,
figure out what the easy thing is to do,
to do, take that.
off the table. It's always wrong. 100%. We're going to have to do very hard things.
We're going to have to do things that don't feel good because they don't gratify our desires.
We're going to have to do things that go against the grain and that are difficult for us.
And part of the reason they're going to be difficult for us is that we've been formed by these
other things. Because we're literally going to be
trying to become a different person, and that's not easy.
Not pretend to be a different person, but actually become a different person.
To actually have things be true of us that maybe aren't true of us today, but we want
them to be true of us in the future, and we're going to have to work and fight to get
to that truth.
And we're going to have to wean ourselves off of a lot of the things that have become
comfortable and pleasurable and it becomes crutches.
for us, right? Life in our world, as we've talked about before, our current world is constructed
in in human way. There is not a way to operate and function successfully in our world as
it's structured today and be sane. Right? And so some of the things we develop, we're
developing as crutches just to try to survive in an insane world. But some of those crutches
R.
alcohol, drugs, pornography,
mindless, mindless entertainment,
patterns of self-destruction,
that we know, while they may be helping me get from today to tomorrow,
they're not helping me become the person I was created to be.
They're not helping me be a human being.
They're not helping me find an experience and give and receive love.
They're not pretty
joy in my life. They're not giving me a sense of peace. They're not bringing peace to the world
around me. They're not solving the problems that are causing me to run to them in the first place.
So my takeaway tonight, right, is that each of us needs to become very deliberate about the
person who we want to be in Christ. And we need to start
with every decision we make, no matter how big or small,
asking ourselves, is this gonna bring me closer
to that person who I was created to be in Christ,
or is this gonna take me farther away?
This could be with decisions that see minor,
right, as minor as what am I gonna have for lunch?
Is it a fast day or not?
Or this can be as major as who should I be dating, who should I marry, what kind of job should
I work at, what kind of career should I pursue, should I pursue a career on down the line?
Because if we aren't doing that thinking, right, if we aren't focusing, right, focusing
is our self and our attention.
on where we want to go, we will get pulled to all kinds of other places that we don't want to go.
But there's always hope.
So long as you're alive, right?
So long as you're alive, you can start making those decisions and start moving in that direction,
no matter how far gone you've gone.
You can start to head in that direction.
But we have to start to act rather than just being acted upon.
We need to start choosing who and what kind of spirit is going to be the organizing principle
of our life, not just falling into whatever one is nearby, and seems attractive at the
moment, or wants to get its hooks in us.
And if we do that, it will not be easy, there will not be a point where it gets easier, there
will not be a point where we've arrived, and it's like, okay, now I can coast.
by Christ.
said, if you want to follow him, you have to pick up your cross and follow him.
The walk you take with a cross ends with you being, you dying upon it.
Right?
But that is the road that leads through the cross to the resurrection,
that leads to eternal life, which is something we begin to experience in this world,
and then continues into the next and ultimately into the life of the world.
to come. Amen. Well, that is our show for tonight everyone. Thank you very much for listening
and tuning in. If you didn't get through to us live, we'd still like to hear from you.
You can email us at LordofSpiritz at AncientFate.com. You can message us at our Facebook page,
or you can leave us a voice mail at SpeakPipe.com slash LordofSpiritz.
Join us for a live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern.
4PM Pacific, but you won't hear them if you're watching Channel Zero.
If you're on Facebook, you can follow our page and join our discussion group.
You can leave reviews and ratings everywhere applicable, but most importantly, share this
show with a friend who is going to love it and be hated or be irritated by it.
You know, never know.
And finally, be sure to go to www.AxianFaith.com.
Stroke Support and help make sure we and lots of AFR podcasts are stay on the air so
You can listen to all of these podcasts in your 98 Oils, which is of course.
Thank you, good night, and may God bless you and Christ is risen.
And do these risen.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits, with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung, a listener-supported presentation of ancient
And I beheld and
And I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts and the elders,
and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 than thousands of thousands, saying with
a loud voice, worthy as the land that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom
and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11-12.
Giving the ancient faith a new voice, this is Ancient Faith Radio.